[SPEAKER_00]: So, this is Majjhima Nikaya 20, Vidaka Santana Sutta, which is, eh... the five strategies for bringing unwholesome thoughts to its rest.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, eh... this is, eh... this is how we chose to translate this title.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the sutra goes by saying here, because when a bhikkhu is giving attention to some sign, owing to that sign, there arise in him evil unwholesome thoughts connected with desire, with hate, with delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, he should give attention to some other sign connected with what's wholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when he gives attention to some other sign, connected with what is wholesome, the evil unwholesome thoughts connected with desire, with hate, with delusion, are abandoned in him and subside.
[SPEAKER_00]: With the abandoning of them, his mind becomes steadied internally, quieted and brought to singleness and composed.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, we spoke about the signs of the mind before.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, maybe we should not get into it now.
[SPEAKER_00]: We'll try and link the talk to the... what signs of the mind are.
[SPEAKER_00]: The point is, so it's not just... it's not about the objects of your senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not about... it's not even about the specific thoughts you might have.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about the signs of the mind in regard to... so it's about a state of the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is then exemplified through thoughts that are revolving in your head, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in this case, it's the state of mind that is affected with desire, hate or delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can know what state of mind you have on account of what thoughts are popping up, persisting and pressuring you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the point here is to see that the problem is not on the level of the thoughts, the problem is on the level of the state of mind behind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why then, you recognize that, hold on, I don't need to battle and fight these thoughts that are assailing me right here, right now, stop them from... my mind from thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: All I need to do is direct that mind to... towards a different theme.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, these thoughts will be replaced, because it's the theme of the mind, the state of the mind, the context, the peripheral, as you often say, that's what determines what thoughts would be coming up for you, what thoughts would be arising, and persisting, and increasing, and pressuring you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the first way.
[SPEAKER_00]: The second way, it says, if he's giving attention to some other sign connected with what is wholesome,
[SPEAKER_00]: These evil unwholesome states still persist.
[SPEAKER_00]: They don't go away.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, he should examine the danger in those thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, then, he should start, again, seeing the danger of that state of mind that is exemplified through these thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, am I welcoming the thoughts of, say, ill-will?
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I accepting them mentally and allowing my mind to revolve around them even further?
[SPEAKER_00]: And if so, then you should start contemplating danger in doing that very thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not about seeing the danger in the thoughts that arise on their own or something, that just appear.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's seeing the danger in you accepting them, welcoming them, delighting in them and acting out of them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that... that can then help.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, and then the simile here says, just as a man or a woman, young, youthful, fond of ornaments, would be horrified, humiliated and disgusted if the carcass of a snake or a dog or a human being were hung around his or her neck.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the attitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: You should be disgusted and horrified by your choice of entertainment of such thoughts of anger or lust and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not horrified and disgusted by
[SPEAKER_00]: An object of a thought in itself that has appeared on its own, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's not your responsibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your responsibility and the disgust should come from the recognition that you are the one accepting this and welcoming it and delighting in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or in other words, practically speaking, am I consciously, am I choosing, am I saying yes to the pressure to resolve these thoughts and get involved with them?
[SPEAKER_00]: So what I'm referring to is like, say you do have a mind that doesn't want to let go of something and your thoughts are pressuring you and the mind is just revolving around it and the thoughts are just popping up and going...
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to get rid of the discomfort of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Say, somebody upsets you, you're angry, so it's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, usually people go about getting rid of that by acting out, saying something, harming the other and then feeling satisfied on account of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But fundamentally, the problem was you refused to bear the discomfort of that state of mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, say, on the other hand, you don't quite act out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Physically, you don't act out.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't do anything bad and unwholesome verbally either.
[SPEAKER_00]: But mentally, you are still choosing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, there's like a... imagine like... well, you don't imagine, just remember.
[SPEAKER_00]: Last time, you had like a like a compulsive type of
[SPEAKER_00]: Thinking, pressuring in your mind, revolving around it, when there, you know, there might be like a sort of like a spike in the pressure and so on, and then you're enduring it, and thoughts are sort of popping up, and trying to make you act.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then there's always a time when you willingly, kind of, bitterly almost, accept and then plunge yourself further in those thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but still... and then you carry on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, sure, then you can't stop it, because you gave it the momentum.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then again, the momentum starts fading away, because it will go as far as you pushed it previously.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's usually people kind of don't even recognize the fact that they were the one pushing it every now and then.
[SPEAKER_00]: They were the one adding fuel to the fire every now and then.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, all they see is, wow, this momentum never stops and I'm fully subject to it and I don't know what to do, how to stop this mind from thinking these thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: All you need to do is not make those bitter choices, those little subtle, yeah, okay, I'll just give in to resolve this thought that bothers me, and then be patient.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it will have to run its course.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you know, there might be some like a more ambiguous pressure trying to make you pick it up again, but unless you're careless, or unless you willingly choose to pick it up again, it cannot pick itself up.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the that's the important point here.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, number three.
[SPEAKER_00]: If, while he's examining the danger in those thoughts, those thoughts are still not resting, they're not put to rest, then he should try to ignore them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he should not give attention to those thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he should recognize, and that's kind of on the level seeing the mind as mind, seeing the state of the mind regardless of what thoughts are there, coming or going.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, first you just try it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, thoughts are there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, they're unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let me contemplate a more wholesome theme.
[SPEAKER_00]: That can then change the state of this mind that revolves around these thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, hopefully, these thoughts will go away.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if that fails, then you look for the danger in accepting those thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then they will go away, because you stopped accepting them, you stopped welcoming them in.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now, if that doesn't work either, then just ignore the thoughts and stay mindful of your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just stay mindful of the state of the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: And again, see, the danger is kind of still seen.
[SPEAKER_00]: It might not be helping you, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: For these thoughts to leave you alone, but nevertheless, the danger is seen, which means, if you just stay mindful of the state of the mind, so the signs of your mind, that reveal what state is in, so you should just use that as a container.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you know, like, I don't need to worry about the specific thoughts, as long as I stay
[SPEAKER_00]: Recollected, within this state of mind that endures for as long as it endures, I won't do anything foolish, I won't do anything stupid, I won't do anything careless.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then these thoughts, because now you're really not paying any attention to them, so to speak, you are concerned with the state of the mind and state of the mind alone, those thoughts could hopefully go away, or go to rest.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: 4.
[SPEAKER_00]: If while ignoring and trying to forget those thoughts, and not giving attention to them, still unwholesome thoughts arise, then he should give attention to stilling the thought formation of those thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when he gives attention to stilling the thought formation, so the thought activity,
[SPEAKER_00]: Deactivation, how we translate it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, any unwholesome thoughts connected with desire, with hate and delusion, would be abandoned and just subside.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, with the abandoning of them, his mind becomes steady internally, quiet and brought to singleness and composed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just as a man walking fast might consider, why am I walking fast?
[SPEAKER_00]: What if I walk slowly?
[SPEAKER_00]: If he would walk slowly, then he might consider, why am I walking slowly?
[SPEAKER_00]: What if I stand?
[SPEAKER_00]: If he would stand, then he might consider, why am I standing?
[SPEAKER_00]: What if I sit?
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, if he would sit, he might consider, why am I sitting?
[SPEAKER_00]: What if I lay down?
[SPEAKER_00]: By doing so, he would substitute each grosser posture for one that was subtler.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this pertains basically to the activity, the thought formation, the thought saṅkhara, the saṅkhara of your thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the activity of your thoughts, it's like...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you are not, as I said, as I often say,
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't have to worry about the actual thought in itself being present, but see, the activity of a thought is something you're already engaged with.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just as I added earlier, it's that, like for example, one of the activities that would be fueling, one that would be forming your thoughts further, is that choice that one would make towards
[SPEAKER_00]: Resolving a thought, or dealing with it, or addressing it, or whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the coarseness of that choice would be the strength of the activity.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you're like really just keep picking it up,
[SPEAKER_00]: In that, like, a bitter way that offers you a possibility of... but it will resolve itself if I just keep, you know, if I go back to one more time and address this thought and address that and who said what and when and how.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the activities that you can start refining.
[SPEAKER_00]: You realize, well, wait, what if I just don't do this choice and then, like,
[SPEAKER_00]: Endure the pressure of choosing, instead of enduring the pressure of thoughts that have been chosen and now revolving out of your control.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then that choice can be refined further and further and further.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's that recognition.
[SPEAKER_00]: But mind you, this is not something you could just do first.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is when all the other things fail, which means you were able to successfully do all the other things beforehand.
[SPEAKER_00]: You were... you know how to not pay attention to thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are skilled in seeing the signs of your mind and see the state of the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yes, if you fulfill those previous three steps, methods, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: The time will come when some thoughts would still persist, because they are subtler, dead, more deeply rooted, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you actually have to deactivate them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's say like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Deactivate them by refining your involvement with those thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the reason why I'm pointing this out is because, again, somebody reads this image and might think, oh, these are just like five ways, and I'll pick and choose and do this sometimes and do that sometimes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, if you're skilled in all five, you can do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there is a reason that they're listed in this order.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is a reason that the Buddha doesn't start telling somebody, yeah, calm your mind by stilling the thought formation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, you know, what will they make of it?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you are already familiar with the nature of, you know, pressuring thoughts, not welcoming, not delighting, ignoring them when necessary, not forgetting the state of mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, if you have
[SPEAKER_00]: If you have trained yourself long enough in enduring thoughts without acting out of them, the time will come when you're going to start recognizing these more subtler forms of your engagement with your own thinking, like how you're taking it up, let's say, like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you're going to say, wait a minute, so what if I don't take it up in this manner?
[SPEAKER_00]: What if I don't take up this thinking as much?
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you realize, oh, that's all it was enough for this thought to be put to rest.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's specifically a thought activation, a thought saṅkhara.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, things that are basically keeping the thought active, let's say like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And those things, it's exactly welcoming, delighting, entertaining, not seeing the danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of those are your attitudes, your ways, coarse ways or coarser ways of taking up those very thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you have been training the previous three ways and enduring the thoughts sufficiently enough, not acting out of them, you're going to start seeing this subtle attitude as something that, oh... or rather, let's say like, you're going to find yourself doing
[SPEAKER_00]: Or holding these attitudes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're not going to see the attitude, sort of, oh, look, I chose it and it came to be.
[SPEAKER_00]: You will find yourself delighting in a thought, but when you do, that would be enough to stop delighting.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you might find yourself in a course, coarsely, sort of, gripped by whatever, revolving around and taking up and trying to deal with something, trying to get rid of it, trying to manage it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you catch yourself up, you catch that attitude behind those thoughts, behind your involvement with them.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when you do catch that attitude, then it will... that will be enough to drop it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, if even that doesn't work, and the thoughts are still pressuring you, and the enduring of them is still unpleasant, the fifth way is just bear it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You did all you can, now you just have to bear until these thoughts go away on their own.
[SPEAKER_00]: With his teeth clenched and tongue pressed against the roof of his mouth, he should beat down, constrain and crush the mind with the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you just basically take on the state of mind, whichever way it is, and you just say no.
[SPEAKER_00]: And endure it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Endure it, kicking and screaming, until it calms down.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, bear it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, the simile is, just as a strong man might seize a weaker man by the head or shoulders and beat him down, constrain him and crush him,
[SPEAKER_00]: With his teeth clenched and he's talking, that's how he should do it to his mind, until that mind becomes steady and internally quieted and brought to singleness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, these are the ways of... the five ways of resting the thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not... they're not the five ways of getting rid of the thoughts, because, again, that's predicated on a view that thoughts in themselves are the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the pressure behind the thoughts, and that pressure behind the thoughts that you have to endure is due to your state of mind towards those thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there are a few statements and questions regarding these passages we just read.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there seems to be a difference between thought and thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, a thought is a kind of intentional mental image that one can choose to think about or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thought arises and exerts pressure on me to think it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, you can say that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, and that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: The thought presents itself and it can reveal the underlying problem, if there is one.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you wouldn't have a thought infused with sensual desire, without a mind that's already leaning towards sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thought in itself is not a problem, but yes, what you then keep choose to think around it,
[SPEAKER_00]: Through either your attitude of, I must get rid of this because it bothers me, I need more of this because it pressures me, and so on, that's now your involvement and your responsibility, and that's really the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the second question is, these instructions seem to be the five ways of enduring a thought, so as to remove the fuel that sustains the unwholesome thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that fuel brings one direct interference with it, by the way, of denial, resistance, acceptance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the simile we often say.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, you know, somebody comes at your door, starts yelling or screaming or trying to seduce you to get out and all of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You might think that's a problem, and then you open the door, and you get out, and get all involved, get into a fight, or chase them, or follow them, and you realize, oh, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: The problem is, basically, all they want is to get you out of the house.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it doesn't matter how much they're in front of your door, and how often they pressure you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Unless you choose to open that door, unless you choose to get involved on that level of the mind, then you'll be... there will be no problems.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's not to say that, you know, when the
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not that you choose to do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the symptom of you basically not seeing the signs of your mind correctly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'm qualifying this, because sometimes a person might think, okay, so I will not open the door and all this kind of compulsive thinking will stop on its own.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yes, if you correctly not open the door, that will happen.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the problem is, first you need to see the door.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, and in order to see the door, you need to see the signs that point where that door is.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to recognize the state of mind, regardless of the thoughts that are kind of pressuring and revolving in front of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Usually, when the mind is gripped by something, say, again, some compulsive theme that you can't let go of, whatever it might be, your attitude is implying that it's the thinking that's the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why you're not seeing where the mind is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because your mind, basically, is implying that it's there.
[SPEAKER_00]: The problem is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not, don't look here, look over there.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, the more you look at the thoughts, the more you fuel them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're obviously way out, the door wide open, and then, eh... and then you don't even see the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why I always say that it's that endurance, not welcoming, not acting out, that has to come first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, you're gonna probably have quite a few episodes of compulsively, neurotically, mind revolving around stuff, and it won't listen to you, and it won't drop it, and you realize, okay, so basically, I need to endure it until it tires out.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's all the similes the Buddha was talking about.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, in reference to taming the mind, like getting a wild elephant in... You don't get a wild elephant and immediately start issuing commands.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just... it doesn't work.
[SPEAKER_00]: You get a wild elephant...
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, chain it, put the chain in a strong peg in the ground and then just wait until it completely gets tired from kicking and screaming, which is what it's going to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, another reason why this is important to keep in mind is because people will easily assume that these five ways of resting or making your thoughts rest or dealing with the thoughts are applicable on the level of that compulsive thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: If there is a compulsive thinking going on,
[SPEAKER_00]: Means, oh, you are fully gripped by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no signs of the mind that are being noticed, because that's what feeds the compulsion.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you recognize the compulsion is a symptom, then, of me not seeing what I need to see, and in order to do it, I need to wait for this to to tire itself out.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you recognize what thoughts are rising, persisting, what are pressuring you, and then you can even foresee them, before they actually are fully actualized, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, so, in other way, like, I think, before any of these five ways become applicable, a person needs to do a great deal of endurance of their own thoughts and their own mind without acting out of it or without trying to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, these are not methods of getting rid of the thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're methods of of taming your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Third statement.
[SPEAKER_00]: In brief, it seems to me that one leaves the thought alone while doing something else, which indirectly results in unwholesome thought, which is persisting in the background, dying out.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like trying to remove an unwanted guest
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like trying to remove an unwanted guest without any indication to him that you're doing so, because if he notices that you're trying to remove him, he stays longer or just pretends to leave, just so that he can return later to watch you struggle again.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I think you can say that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's... if you go head-on,
[SPEAKER_00]: Against these thoughts, as I said, means, ah, you're basically of a view, your mind is of an implication that that's where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You acknowledged.
[SPEAKER_00]: You acknowledge the fact that you were affected by the pressure of the thoughts and that's all the thoughts want.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whether you try to get rid of them or say yes to them, the point is you are fueling them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how do you get rid of them without making them know you're trying to get rid of them?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, by first not showing signs of any disturbance on account of their presence.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, no matter how close they get, you learn how to operate without acting out, without kicking and screaming, without, you know, trying to push them away and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, they can't see that you're affected.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you can actually start operating within that, that will be... well, you will become invisible, let's say like that, to them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, you can actually... you can deal with them properly.
[SPEAKER_00]: These strategies are the middle way practices.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: And thus, they're quite subtle.
[SPEAKER_00]: They help you endure the pressure of the unwholesome and in doing so de-pressure the situation by not contributing towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the pressure, say, unwanted guests, back to the just the recent simile, the pressure there is not the... it's not the guest.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's you resisting the discomfort of that guest.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you're pressured.
[SPEAKER_00]: So if you learn how to de-pressurize yourself,
[SPEAKER_00]: For lack of a better word.
[SPEAKER_00]: Regardless of whether there's a guest there or trying to enter or so on, you'll be at peace.
[SPEAKER_00]: No problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like a longer question.
[SPEAKER_00]: I used to try to get rid of lustful thinking by doing various things like a subha contemplation, cold showers, mowing the lawn and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And although it worked in the beginning, I still on later occasions gave in to lustful thinking, which meant that I had to do a subha and everything else again.
[SPEAKER_00]: I realized that this would go on forever and that was, as you say, not dealing with the roots of the problem, but only with its symptoms.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, so...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's management.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's what we often say in many other talks, like uprooting versus management.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's that's the fundamental difference here.
[SPEAKER_00]: And again, bear that in mind even when you read this sutra paragraph.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is not management.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is uprooting.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're not just trying to get rid of these thoughts because they bother me.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you're trying to basically uproot the state of the mind that makes these thoughts bother you and keep coming back for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I find that Majjhima Nikāt 20, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's that's the whole... the simile of the trap.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, you think
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, I must deal with this thought, but... and thought presents itself as something... No, listen, if you deal with this, if you follow this desire, you'll be satisfied.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you, you know, get rid of this discomfort, you know, of your aversion, everything will be fall back into place.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how the thought presents itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it traps you and lures you out.
[SPEAKER_00]: But really, all the thought wants to do is for you to acknowledge it.
[SPEAKER_00]: To acknowledge it, in a sense, through denying it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, in order to deny something, you need to recognize it, you need to act out towards it, or to affirm it, or even to, like, just...
[SPEAKER_00]: Be delusional about it, let's say like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not even know where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the last point is, for the one who applies these strategies on the right level, one must be able to discern the signs of the mind, the citta, nimitta, intentions before and behind one's actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: By taking the fuel away from the unwholesome intentions, one will not have to deal with the unwholesome thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that that's kind of sums it up.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the the fuel.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's the five ways of unplugging
[SPEAKER_00]: The energy that fuels your thoughts of the unwholesome kind.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the Buddha finishes this by saying if a monk with the right view correctly practices all of this, he'll be the master of his thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: He'll be able to think whatever he wants to think and not think whatever he doesn't want to think.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, his mind will be completely tamed and his mind will obey his will.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will listen to him.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will do what He tells it to do.